<ac:structured-macro ac:name="excerpt">
  <ac:parameter ac:name="atlassian-macro-output-type">BLOCK</ac:parameter>
  <ac:rich-text-body>
    <p>Detected Filterbank data is a time-frequency Observatory Data Product used for discovering and characterising pulsars and transient events like fast radio bursts.</p>
  </ac:rich-text-body>
</ac:structured-macro>
<h2>What is Detected Filterbank Data?</h2>
<p>Detected Filterbank (DFB) data is a specialised Observatory Data Product designed for discovering and characterising transient and periodic phenomena in radio observations. It consists of time-frequency intensity measurements optimised for pulsar and fast radio burst (FRB) searches.</p>
<h2>Data Characteristics</h2>
<h3>Structure</h3>
<p>Detected Filterbank data has the following structure:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Time axis:</strong> Sequential samples from the observation, typically at millisecond or sub-millisecond resolution</li>
  <li><strong>Frequency axis:</strong> Filterbank channels spanning the observation bandwidth, typically 10–100 MHz resolution per channel</li>
  <li><strong>Polarisation:</strong> Linear (XX, XY, YX, YY) or Stokes parameters (I, Q, U, V)</li>
  <li><strong>Intensity:</strong> Real-valued power or amplitude, after RF band-limiting and detection</li>
</ul>
<h3>Format and Encoding</h3>
<p>DFB data is produced by the SKA signal processing pipeline and archived in standard formats including:</p>
<ul>
  <li>FITS-format filterbank files compatible with standard radio astronomy tools</li>
  <li>HDF5 binary archives for efficient storage and access</li>
  <li>Metadata headers documenting observation parameters, calibration, and processing</li>
</ul>
<h2>Production Pipeline</h2>
<h3>Signal Path</h3>
<p>Detected Filterbank data is generated by the SKA signal processing pipeline via the following steps:</p>
<ol>
  <li><strong>RF Band-Limiting:</strong> Wide-bandwidth antenna signals are filtered to the observation band</li>
  <li><strong>Channelisation:</strong> The band is divided into narrow frequency channels by a polyphase filterbank or FFT</li>
  <li><strong>Detection:</strong> Power or intensity is computed for each time-frequency bin (often via squared magnitude of complex visibilities or beamformed outputs)</li>
  <li><strong>Integration:</strong> Time-frequency samples may be integrated over short intervals to control data volume</li>
  <li><strong>Formatting:</strong> Data are packaged into standard archive formats with full metadata</li>
</ol>
<h3>Calibration</h3>
<p>DFB data includes:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Flux density calibration relative to known radio sources</li>
  <li>Bandpass calibration to correct for frequency-dependent gain variations</li>
  <li>Gain and phase correction metadata</li>
  <li>RFI flagging information indicating contaminated samples</li>
</ul>
<h2>Science Use Cases</h2>
<h3>Pulsar Discovery and Timing</h3>
<p>DFB data enables efficient pulsar searches via dedispersion and folding algorithms. Key applications include:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Discovery of new millisecond pulsars and ultra-long-period objects</li>
  <li>Pulsar timing measurements for gravitational wave detection via pulsar timing arrays</li>
  <li>Characterisation of pulsar emission mechanisms and magnetosphere physics</li>
</ul>
<h3>Fast Radio Burst (FRB) Detection</h3>
<p>The time-frequency structure of DFB data is ideal for identifying impulsive transients:</p>
<ul>
  <li>FRB discovery and localisation through multi-beam transient identification</li>
  <li>Measurement of dispersion measure and rotation measure</li>
  <li>Statistical studies of the FRB population</li>
</ul>
<h3>General Transient Searches</h3>
<p>Beyond pulsars and FRBs, DFB data can be used to search for:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Rotating transients and rotating radio transients (RRATs)</li>
  <li>Sporadic burst sources and orphan afterglows</li>
  <li>Magnetars and other exotic neutron star phenomena</li>
</ul>
<h2>Data Volume and Storage</h2>
<h3>Typical Data Rates</h3>
<p>DFB data rates depend on observation configuration:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>SKA-Low observations:</strong> Approximately 100 GB to 1 TB per observation hour (frequency-dependent)</li>
  <li><strong>SKA-Mid observations:</strong> Similar ranges with different frequency coverage and resolution trade-offs</li>
</ul>
<p>These rates reflect a balance between scientific sensitivity (fine time-frequency resolution) and archive storage constraints. Integration and selective archival strategies are employed to manage volume.</p>
<h3>Archival and Retention</h3>
<p>All DFB data are archived in the SKA Archive with:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Comprehensive metadata indexing for discovery</li>
  <li>Long-term preservation guarantees</li>
  <li>On-demand access and download capabilities</li>
</ul>
<h2>Access and Analysis</h2>
<h3>Downloading DFB Data</h3>
<p>Users can search for and download DFB data via the SKA Archive portal using filters such as:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Observation date and time</li>
  <li>Sky region (RA/Dec or object name)</li>
  <li>Frequency range</li>
  <li>Observation type (pulsar, transient, blind survey)</li>
  <li>Quality metrics and RFI levels</li>
</ul>
<h3>Analysis Pipelines</h3>
<p>Standard tools for working with DFB data include:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>PRESTO:</strong> Pulsar searching and analysis</li>
  <li><strong>SIGPROC:</strong> Filterbank file manipulation and processing</li>
  <li><strong>Your:</strong> Your Unified Reduction code for modern Python-based analysis</li>
</ul>
<p>The SKA provides containerised versions of these tools and example Jupyter notebooks to help new users get started.</p>
<h3>Cloud-Based Analysis</h3>
<p>For large DFB datasets, users can run analysis directly on archive-hosted data via SKA computational services, avoiding the need to download multi-terabyte files locally.</p>
<ac:structured-macro ac:name="note">
  <ac:parameter ac:name="title">Related Data Products</ac:parameter>
  <ac:rich-text-body>
    <p>See also <ac:link><ac:plain-text-link-body>Pulsar Timing Observatory Data Product</ac:plain-text-link-body></ac:link> for high-precision timing measurements and <ac:link><ac:plain-text-link-body>Introduction to Observatory Data Products and Advanced Data Products</ac:plain-text-link-body></ac:link> for the full ODP suite.</p>
  </ac:rich-text-body>
</ac:structured-macro>
