<ac:structured-macro ac:name="excerpt">
  <ac:parameter ac:name="atlassian-macro-output-type">BLOCK</ac:parameter>
  <ac:rich-text-body>
    <p>Observatory Data Products (ODPs) are standard pipeline outputs from SKA. Advanced Data Products (ADPs) are community-derived science products built from ODPs.</p>
  </ac:rich-text-body>
</ac:structured-macro>
<h2>Introduction to Data Products</h2>
<p>The SKA produces two categories of data products that feed scientific discovery: <strong>Observatory Data Products (ODPs)</strong> produced by the SKA data processing pipeline, and <strong>Advanced Data Products (ADPs)</strong> developed by the research community or the observatory.</p>
<h2>Observatory Data Products (ODPs)</h2>
<h3>What Are ODPs?</h3>
<p>Observatory Data Products are standardised, calibrated outputs of the SKA Science Data Processor (SDP). They represent the primary data products guaranteed to be produced and archived for every science observation.</p>
<h3>ODP Types</h3>
<p>The standard ODP suite includes:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Continuum Images:</strong> Integrated intensity maps across broad frequency ranges, suitable for source detection, morphology studies, and wide-field surveys</li>
  <li><strong>Spectral-Line Cubes:</strong> Three-dimensional data with two spatial dimensions and frequency dimension, enabling velocity-resolved science</li>
  <li><strong>Visibility Data:</strong> Raw calibrated interferometric visibilities, enabling independent re-analysis and alternative processing approaches</li>
  <li><strong>Pulsar Timing Products:</strong> High-precision arrival time measurements, timing residuals, and pulse profiles from pulsar observations</li>
  <li><strong>Detected Filterbank Data:</strong> Time-frequency data for transient and pulsar searches</li>
  <li><strong>Flowthrough Archive Data:</strong> Subset of calibrated visibilities archived continuously for serendipitous discovery and reprocessing</li>
</ul>
<h3>ODP Characteristics</h3>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Standardised:</strong> Produced using consistent pipeline configurations and algorithms</li>
  <li><strong>Quality Assured:</strong> Subject to automated quality checks and validation</li>
  <li><strong>Reproducible:</strong> Includes full processing metadata for reproducibility and validation</li>
  <li><strong>Archived:</strong> Permanently stored in the SKA Archive with indexed metadata</li>
  <li><strong>Discoverable:</strong> Findable via the SKA Archive portal with comprehensive search and filtering</li>
</ul>
<h2>Advanced Data Products (ADPs)</h2>
<h3>What Are ADPs?</h3>
<p>Advanced Data Products are higher-level science products derived from ODPs. ADPs are produced by the research community, international collaborations, or the SKA observatory itself, and represent value-added analysis of ODP data.</p>
<h3>ADP Examples</h3>
<p>Common ADPs include:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Source Catalogues:</strong> Lists of detected sources with properties (positions, fluxes, classifications) extracted from continuum images</li>
  <li><strong>Spectral-Line Catalogues:</strong> Detections and measurements from spectral-line cubes (e.g., HI surveys, galaxy redshifts)</li>
  <li><strong>Mosaics:</strong> Combination of multiple observations into larger sky maps</li>
  <li><strong>Stacked Products:</strong> Co-addition of multiple observations or sources for enhanced sensitivity</li>
  <li><strong>Derived Properties:</strong> Physical quantities computed from ODP measurements (e.g., stellar masses, star formation rates)</li>
  <li><strong>Machine Learning Models:</strong> Trained classifiers, regression models, or anomaly detection outputs</li>
</ul>
<h3>ADP Production and Curation</h3>
<p>ADPs may be:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Community-generated:</strong> Produced by research teams using public ODP data and their own analysis tools</li>
  <li><strong>Collaboration products:</strong> Generated by large survey collaborations or working groups</li>
  <li><strong>Observatory-curated:</strong> High-value ADPs validated and endorsed by the SKA observatory for broad community use</li>
</ul>
<p>Community-generated ADPs can be submitted to the SKA Archive for curation and long-term preservation, making them discoverable alongside ODPs.</p>
<h2>The ODP–ADP Relationship</h2>
<p>ODPs and ADPs form a data processing continuum:</p>
<table>
  <colgroup><col /></colgroup>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>ODP</strong> ← Raw calibrated observation product from SDP pipeline</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>↓ (community or SKAO analysis)</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>ADP</strong> ← Science-ready higher-level product (catalogues, mosaics, etc.)</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
<p>This design allows the SKA to:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Provide robust, standardised data products to all users</li>
  <li>Enable diverse science analyses through the ADP ecosystem</li>
  <li>Avoid reproducing pipeline computations unnecessarily</li>
  <li>Preserve the intellectual contributions of research teams</li>
</ul>
<h2>Quality Levels and Validation</h2>
<h3>ODP Quality Assurance</h3>
<p>All ODPs undergo automated quality checks including:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Beam and noise characterisation</li>
  <li>Astrometric and photometric calibration validation</li>
  <li>Radio frequency interference (RFI) flagging quality</li>
  <li>Pipeline execution logs and error checking</li>
</ul>
<p>Quality metrics are recorded in the ODP metadata for user assessment.</p>
<h3>ADP Quality and Provenance</h3>
<p>Community ADPs carry detailed provenance information documenting:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Source ODP identifiers and versions</li>
  <li>Analysis software, algorithms, and parameters</li>
  <li>Validation and testing procedures</li>
  <li>Known limitations and caveats</li>
</ul>
<p>This transparency enables users to assess the reliability and applicability of ADPs for their science.</p>
<h2>Integration with the SKA Science Archive</h2>
<p>Both ODPs and ADPs are discoverable and accessible through the centralised <strong>SKA Science Archive</strong>:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Unified search:</strong> Find ODPs and ADPs with common query interfaces</li>
  <li><strong>Metadata indexing:</strong> Full-text and structured searches across all product attributes</li>
  <li><strong>Download and streaming:</strong> Access raw files or stream subsets on demand</li>
  <li><strong>Computational access:</strong> Run analysis directly on archive-hosted data via cloud services</li>
</ul>
<ac:structured-macro ac:name="tip">
  <ac:parameter ac:name="title">For Data Producers</ac:parameter>
  <ac:rich-text-body>
    <p>If you are developing Advanced Data Products, see the ADP submission guidelines in the Archive documentation to register your products and make them discoverable to the global community.</p>
  </ac:rich-text-body>
</ac:structured-macro>
